Hello, AP
U.S. History students.  Here is the
third period in three
minutes.  So, the third
period begins in
1754 with the French and
Indian War.  It
was part of a
larger conflict,
but in America it
flared up over
British expansion
into the Ohio River Valley,
which was controlled by
French traders
and Native American
tribes.  The war
ended with the
Treaty of Paris
in 1763, which
radically changed
the relationship between
the colonists and the
British Crown.    That
same year,
Pontiac's Rebellion occurred,
leading to the
adoption
of the Proclamation of 1763.
It prohibited
settlement beyond
the Appalachians to
prevent further
conflicts with the
indigenous population.
After the war, Britain was
also left with a
huge debt.  This
forced her to end her
policy of "salvific
non-intervention", which
angered the colonists
.  Tensions were growing in the colonies
over
new taxes, such as the
Stamp Act of
1765.  Groups such
as the Sons of Liberty and the
Daughters of Liberty
protested with the
famous slogan: "
No taxation without
representation."  And
if the Boston
Massacre of 1770
angered the colonists
, the Boston
Tea Party of 1773
angered the Crown,
leading to the
passage of the
Intolerable Acts.
Despite attempts to
keep the peace at the
First
Continental
Congress, shots rang out near
Lexington and
Concord,
leading
to the convening of the Second
Continental
Congress.  And after
Thomas Paine's Common Sense
convinced the colonists
that independence was the
best way, the Declaration of Independence
was drafted on July 4, 1776
.  Both
documents were
inspired by Enlightenment ideas
such as
republicanism and
natural rights.
Despite being outnumbered
, the
Continental Army
won the
American
Revolution thanks to
the leadership of George
Washington,
the use of
guerrilla
tactics, and the support of
allies, particularly
the French.  The war
ended in 1783 with
another
Treaty of Paris, which granted
America independence
.  But the new state
had a lot of problems,
mostly because
the leaders deliberately
created a weak
government—the Articles of
Confederation.  The
Articles had no
authority to collect
taxes or
create a
national currency.
There was only a
legislative branch of
government, where each state
had one vote.
Since nine votes were required to
pass a law
and
13 to amend the Articles, the
federal government had
little power.  This
became evident when
they failed to
suppress the
Shays Rebellion.  This led to the
Constitutional
Convention of 1787, where
delegates
proposed a number of
compromises for the
new government.  The "
Great Compromise"
created a bicameral
parliament, and the
controversial "
Three-
Fifths Compromise" appeased
Southerners by
partially including
slaves in determining
the number of
representatives.
The Constitution also
included the ideas of
separation of powers, a
system of checks and
balances, and
federalism.  But
Federalists and
Anti-Federalists
argued over
the ratification of the new
Constitution.
The Anti-Federalists
feared that the new
government would be too
powerful and insisted
on the adoption of a Bill
of Rights.  But
the Federalists, led by
Alexander
Hamilton,
published The
Federalist to
advocate for a new,
stronger government.
Ultimately, the Constitution
was ratified in
1789, and the Bill of
Rights was added to
protect
civil liberties
.  Under the new
Constitution, George
Washington
was unanimously elected the
first president of
America.  While in office,
he set many
precedents, such as
creating the first
presidential
cabinet and
demonstrating
federal power
during the Whiskey Rebellion
.  He also
started the
tradition of two
terms, leaving
office in 1796.  It was then that
he delivered his
famous farewell
address, one of the
most important
documents in
American
history.  In it, he
warned
Americans not to
interfere in
European affairs and to avoid
political parties.
However, in the third
period we also
see America's first
political parties
.
Alexander
Hamilton's Federalist Party sought
an economy
based on
trade and
manufacturing,
supported a
National Bank, and
favored a
liberal interpretation
of the Constitution.
In contrast,
Thomas
Jefferson's Democratic-Republican Party wanted an
agrarian state,
opposed a
National Bank,
and supported a
strict interpretation
of the Constitution.    The
American
Revolution also
inspired revolutions around the
world,
including in France and
Haiti.  The French
Revolution became a
major subject of
foreign policy controversy
between these political
parties.  The third
period ends with
the presidency of John
Adams, the only
Federalist president in
American history.  His
term was
marred by the "Quasi-
War" with France, and
he lost
re-election, partly
over
alien laws and
sedition charges.  Thanks for
watching;  if you
need help with
APUSH, like
tutorials,
timelines, and summary videos
,
be sure
to check out the Ultimate Review
Packet.